Robert G. Mead, Jr. Papers
© 2005 University of Connecticut
Robert G. Mead, Jr. Papers.
1939-2000.
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center.
Robert G. Mead, Jr.
6 linear feet.
Born in Cleveland in 1913, Mead spent most of his early years in Mexico, developing great facility in both English and Spanish. He worked for the OSS during World War II gathering intelligence from Latin American periodicals. After receiving his Ph.D. in 1949, Mead became a professor at the University of Connecticut. In addition to a long and prestigious career as a teacher of foreign languages, Mead was a prolific scholar on Hispanic literature and an advocate for improved Inter-American relations. He also edited the journal Hispania from 1957 to 1962. Mead traveled the world as a lecturer and as an advisor on the teaching of Spanish. He passed away in 1995.
MSS19990027
Biography
Robert G. Mead, Jr. was born in 1913 in Cleveland, Ohio. His father, an engineer, relocated to Mexico eight months later. It was in Mexico that Mead spent most of his first twenty years, living in Tampico and later in Mexico City. He attended the University at California at Berkeley for a brief period in the middle 1930s, but had to drop out for financial reasons. He taught English at a private academy in Mexico from 1936-1937. After his return to the U.S., Mead enrolled at UCLA, where he received his M.A. in Spanish literature in 1942. Mead then traveled east to work for the Office of Strategic Services in Washington, D.C. There, he surveyed Latin America n periodicals for matters relating to American intelligence, preparing a report on a Mexican political group suspected of having Nazi leanings.
Upon leaving the employ of the government in 1947, Mead went to the University of Michigan, and in 1949 finished his doctoral thesis on Peruvian essayist, Manuel Gonzalez Prada, which was written entirely in Spanish. Shortly thereafter, Mead accepted a full-time post at the University of Connecticut.
While engaged in teaching at the University of Connecticut, Mead contributed a number of articles on Hispanic and Latin American literature to scholarly journals. Many of Mead's writings appeared in the journal Hispania in a section called “The Hispanic World.” Mead was also the editor of Hispania from 1957 to 1962. In the early 1960s Mead worked with the Modern Language Association's newly established summer language institute program. As part of this program, Mead traveled the country and made on-site evaluations of over 42 programs. In later years Mead served on the editorial boards of other academic journals and worked with organizations dedicated to the promotion of foreign language education and intercultural understanding. Mead lectured at more than thirty universities and accepted several visiting professorships while maintaining close ties with the University of Connecticut.
Mead received the prestigious Florence Steiner Award for Leadership in Foreign Language Education in 1982. He retired from the University of Connecticut in 1984, but thereafter maintained a high level of scholarly activity. Mead passed away in 1995.
Mead was a dedicated teacher, an active scholar, and a pioneering multiculturalist. The numerous tributes received by Mead during his life and after his death are a testament to his profound impact on the teaching of foreign languages. An outspoken advocate for improved Inter-American relations, he stressed the need for an awareness of Latin American history and culture.
Scope and Content
The materials in this collection were originally collected and organized by Mead's wife, Harriet. Most of the materials are personal papers that came from Mead's office and desktop. Harriet Mead also provided some additional personal materials, such as Mead's notebooks from his collegiate days. Boxes 1 and 2 have been re-organized into folders. The folders contain biographical materials, personal correspondence, manuscript articles by Mead, teaching and presentation materials, newspaper clippings of interest to Mead, and other scholarly articles. Beyond this sequence of folders (in boxes 3 and 4) the collection consists of a number of Mead's notebooks, and several boxes of note cards used in the preparation of scholarly works. A video tape of a memorial service held at the Dodd Center in 1995 is also included.
Removed from the collection: Cultural Survival Quarterly, v. 6, no. 3, Summer 1982. This issue is already catalogued in the APC serials located in the Dodd Center.
Arrangement
Collection consists of a single series. See above for arrangement details.
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining to the University, its history, administration, faculty and staff. In addition, the Dodd Center holds a wide range of Spanish and Latin American periodicals of historical interest. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
Index Terms
This record series is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Persons:
Mead, Robert G., 1913- --Correspondence.
Subjects:
Latin American literature.
Document Types:
Correspondence.; Personal Papers.; Manuscripts (document genre).; Notesbooks.; Publications.; Photographs.; Videotapes.; Clippings (infomration artifacts).
Occupations:
Educators.
Restrictions on Access
There are no access restrictions on this collection.
Acquisition Information
Collection donated to Archives & Special Collections by Harriet Mead in 1999.
Detailed Description
- Series I: Personal Papers, 1939-2000
  - Biographical Articles (by Harriet Mead), Curriculum Vitae, Professional Activities Reports, 1950-2000 (Box 1:, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence supporting Mead's nomination for the Florence Steiner Award for Leadership in Foreign Language Education, 1982 (Box 1:, Folder 2)
  - Publicity and Tribute Materials, 1954-1969 (Box 1:, Folder 3)
  - Publicity and Tribute Materials, 1971-2000 (Box 1:, Folder 4)
  - Memorial Service Notes and Tribute Letters, 1995-1997 (Box 1:, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1946-1972 (Box 1:, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1973-2000 (Box 1:, Folder 7)
  - Letters to the Editor - Latin American Literature, 1956-1967 (Box 1:, Folder 8)
  - Letters to the Editor - U.S. Role in Intercultural Understanding, 1944-1989 (Box 1:, Folder 9)
  - Letters to the Editor - Importance of Foreign Languages, 1953-1988 (Box 1:, Folder 10)
  - Letters to the Editor - Inaccuracies in Language, 1956-1967 (Box 1:, Folder 11)
  - Letters to the Editor - Education Teaching, 1954-1990 (Box 1:, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence with Don Walsh (Hispania editor), 1951-1962 (Box 1:, Folder 13)
  - University of Connecticut Correspondence, 1950-1991 (Box 1:, Folder 14)
  - Studium materials: Correspondence, MS by Mead, ca. 1959 (Box 1:, Folder 15)
  - Modern Language Association Correspondence, 1952-1985 (Box 1:, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence and Reviews regarding Breve historia del ensayo hispanoamericano, 1954-1980 (Box 1:, Folder 17)
  - Organization of American States (OAS-OEA) Correspondence, 1975-1980 (Box 1:, Folder 18)
  - Association of Departments of Foreign Languages (ADFL) Correspondence, 1969-1984 (Box 1:, Folder 19)
  - American Association of Teachers of Spanish and Portuguese (AATSP) Correspondence and Notes, 1955-1995 (Box 1:, Folder 20)
  - American Association of Teachers of Spanish and Portuguese (AATSP) Publications and Newsletters, 1975-1995 (Box 1:, Folder 21)
  - Cuadernos Americanos Correspondence (in Spanish) with index, 1950-1982 (Box 1:, Folder 22)
  - Latin American Research Review Board - Correspondence, Notes, 1965-1968 (Box 1:, Folder 23)
  - Sigma Delta Pi National Spanish Society - Correspondence, Bulletins, 1981-1989 (Box 1:, Folder 24)
  - Notes and Clippings Relating to National Intelligence Service, ca. 1944-1946 (Box 1:, Folder 25)
  - Argentine Literature - clippings, 2 MS articles on Borges, 1968-1969 (Box 1:, Folder 26)
  - Venezuela n Literature - clippings, 1977-1979 (Box 1:, Folder 27)
  - Mario Vargas Llosa - clippings, 1968-1975 (Box 1:, Folder 28)
  - “Manuel Gonzalez Prada: Peruvian Judge of Spain” article MS, correspondence, 1952 (Box 1:, Folder 29)
  - Correspondence from A. Gonzalez Prada, 1942-1943 (Box 1:, Folder 30)
  - Miguel Angel Asturias - Notes, MS, clippings, correspondence, 1967-1974 (Box 1:, Folder 31)
  - Jose Carlos Mariategui - correspondence and photos, 1954-1958 (Box 1:, Folder 32)
  - Gabriel Garcia Marquez - articles and clippings, 1968-1973 (Box 1:, Folder 33)
  - Octoavio Paz Materials, 1972-1993 (Box 1:, Folder 34)
  - Carlos Fuentes - notes, MS, clippings, 1964-1991 (Box 1:, Folder 35)
  - Pablo Neruda - clippings, 1962-1977 (Box 1:, Folder 36)
  - Images of Mexico - articles, clippings, 1974-1980 (Box 1:, Folder 37)
  - Notes and MS articles by Mead on Mexico, 1963-1995 (Box 1:, Folder 38)
  - Clippings on Mexico, 1963-1995 (Box 2:, Folder 39)
  - Articles on Mexico, 1963-1988 (Box 2:, Folder 40)
  - Latin American Literature - articles, clippings, 1963-1995 (Box 2:, Folder 41)
  - Latin American Literature - MS articles by Mead, 1942-1993 (Box 2:, Folder 42)
  - Latin American Literature - MS articles by Mead (in English), 1963-1978 (Box 2:, Folder 43)
  - Latin American Literature - MS articles by Mead (in Spanish), 1951-1980 (Box 2:, Folder 44)
  - Latin American Culture - short articles and presentation notes, ca. 1963-93 (Box 2:, Folder 45)
  - Images of Latin American Culture - presentation notes, ca. 1965-93 (Box 2:, Folder 46)
  - Latin America and the United States - short articles and lecture notes, ca. 1969-80 (Box 2:, Folder 47)
  - Relations between U.S. and Latin America - clippings, 1963-1992 (Box 2:, Folder 48)
  - Latin American Cultural Identity - clippings and materials, 1980-1994 (Box 2:, Folder 49)
  - “Images North and South” and “Intercultural Understanding”, 1962, 1972 (Box 2:, Folder 50)
  - Latin America Culture - MS articles by Mead (in Spanish), 1973-1988 (Box 2:, Folder 51)
  - Columbus Materials - clippings, notes, articles, 1980-1992 (Box 2:, Folder 52)
  - NAFTA Materials - clippings, articles, and notes by Mead, 1994-1995 (Box 2:, Folder 53)
  - Latin American Culture and Politics - Scholarly Articles, 1972-1994 (Box 2:, Folder 54)
  - Miscellaneous Lecture Notes, 1969-1992 (Box 2:, Folder 55)
  - Notes for Talk at Wellesley College, ca. 1985 (Box 2:, Folder 56)
  - Seminario Dominco-Americanio - Presentation Materials, ca. 1982 (Box 2:, Folder 57)
  - Seminario Dominco-Americanio - Conference Materials, ca. 1982 (Box 2:, Folder 58)
  - Teaching Related Articles by Mead, 1971-1986 (Box 2:, Folder 59)
  - Teaching - Presentation Notes (talks to ADFL, others), 1965-1992 (Box 2:, Folder 60)
  - Teaching - Presentation Notes (in Spanish), 1962-1972 (Box 2:, Folder 61)
  - Foreign Language Teaching - Newsletters and Publications, 1954-1986 (Box 2:, Folder 62)
  - Teaching Materials - handouts, Syllabi, Notes, 1967-1988 (Box 2:, Folder 63)
  - NDEA Foreign Language Summer Programs - site visits, evaluations, 1960 (Box 2:, Folder 64)
  - NDEA Foreign Language Summer Programs - correspondence, notes, teaching materials, and evaluations by Mead, 1961-1966 (Box 2:, Folder 65)
  - MLA Foreign Language Materials, 1966-1984 (Box 2:, Folder 66)
  - Clippings on Bilingual Education, 1977-1994 (Box 2:, Folder 67)
  - Clippings and Articles of General Interest to Mead, 1968-1995 (Box 2:, Folder 68)
  - 'English Only' Materials - clippings, correspondence, 1986-1987 (Box 2:, Folder 69)
  - Program Evaluations - Framingham, New Paltz Middlebury College Program Director's Notes, 1983, 1987 (Box 2:, Folder 70)
  - Bibliography of Latin American Literature, 1949-1993 (Box 2:, Folder 71)
  - Various collections of index cards from Mead's papers, ca. 1947-56 (Box 3)
    - - research for thesis on Manuel Gonzalez Prada
    - - teaching materials for classes at University of Michigan
    - - teaching materials for classes at University of Connecticut
    - - bibliography of Spanish American Literature
  - Unprocessed notebooks from UCLA and University of Michigan (student materials), ca. 1939-1949 (Box 4)
  - Videotape of Memorial Service for Mead, 1995
  - Folder containing Mead's degrees, awards, and certificates, 1931-1988
  - Two draft copies and notes relating to Mead's Ph.D. dissertation, 1948-1949 (Box 5)